how important is thinking in practice
hmm it's not optional
so I mean it's not like I say it's not
optional because I know that you know
people specially comes to the Buddhist
practice or you apply to meditation they
think I just need to stop thinking and
they fail to understand that that's a
constriction in terms because that's
another thought I will stop thinking is
a thought it just tries to deny itself
to go around thinking that you would
abstain you from thinking by thinking so
it's impossible to not think only in
second jhana the thoughts would subside
but that's not to say that you stop
thinking just mean you refined your your
your your context and your composure to
the extent that even the movement of the
thoughts now is to course so it's not
like you should stop thinking it's about
you must learn how to think skillfully
to the point of entering the first jhana
which is these the purest way of
thinking you can have thinking and
pondering and that's in itself is enough
for our answer and so what about without
wisdom some people think that wisdom is
who understanding comes from feeling
yeah like the intuitive wisdom that's
another contradiction in terms if it's
intuitive means it's felt if it's felt
means it's not understood because
understanding if you develop
understanding you will be free from
feeling as the Buddha said Alejandro is
developed full understanding of the
experience as a whole he doesn't feel
anything as a result of it that's why
he's cooled down he's in the barn so a
person who feels doesn't understand
exactly the extent you feel to that
extent you're lacking understanding or
wisdom yeah that's that's what wisdom is
it's that understanding I don't mean
understanding in Psychological manner oh
this is what's happening to me I mean
understanding the nature thing
that's what wisdom is wisdom means
perspective we cover that in other talks
basically doesn't mean intelligence
doesn't mean that means perspective and
you don't have or intuitive perspective
that I can't quite put in the words
that's not perspective that's assumed is
defined your own feelings so trying to
understand something a problem hmm
by feeling they're telling what
you know this I've gotta come if I feel
the problem okay
then feeling it experiencing it to
feeling I will understand it and become
wise just through mere feeling it
sipping it well why then we wouldn't
need the whole Dhamma and the Buddhist
teaching before you need to do is feel
it to be free from it while we would
have spent 40 years of teaching how to
free yourself from feeling and suffering
involved with it now whether you choose
to feel it more or not if the problem is
there first and that's a problem in
itself the fact that you're liable to
the problem even if there is no problem
as the Buddha said you recognize M is
subject to sickness aging death
misfortune loss yes I am so now I'm not
sick dying or or losing anything but I
am subjected to it as in I'm liable to
these things they will have to happen so
you don't actually want to wait for that
problem to become acute you want to
recognize it that even without the
problem you are within that liability to
a problem and that's what duque is the
Buddha wasn't sick and dying when he
left the home he saw other people being
sick and dying and then he said oh I'm I
cannot escape this I will this will have
to affect me at some point in the future
and that's the concern that he talks
about but if you wait for the problem to
be affecting you and then to feel it is
just you trying to basically wiggle your
way out of it sort of manage it
psychologize it
deal with it once it has a reason so how
to get wisdom so you get wisdom from
well you get wisdom by developing a
perspective on your own situation such
that perspectives will just what I
described so it's not about when I get a
problem I will do this and then I will
do that and then I will feel this all
that can be in place whatever but you
want to extend that perspective and
realize can I not have any problem in
the future
are the things in me that I'm not
abandoning because of which problems can
land on me suffering can affect me
so you actually that's what wisdom is
preemptively developing perspective to
basically leave the domain where the
problems arise abandoned suffers like
dukkha does not mean suffering means
this is means that uneasiness and you
are uneasy when you don't have any
problem or when you recognize that in a
day or two that's gonna be a big problem
coming your way you don't know what
specific problem it will be but you know
it will have to arise oh you get anxious
you get uneasy see but there is no
problem specifically did she have to
feel and get in touch with yet there is
a problem because you recognize that
liability to a problem is a problem you
can try and feel it all you want it will
not approve your liability only
developing their perspective further and
abandoning passion in regard to it is
what develops their wisdom dead uproots
the liability to it